Finding Aid of the UW-Milwaukee Center for Great Lakes Studies, Office of the Director Records, 1963-1994
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
UW-Milwaukee Center for Great Lakes Studies, Office of the Director Records, 1963-1994
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. Center for Great Lakes Studies. Office of the Director
UWM Archival Collection 59
2.4 cubic ft. (5 boxes)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Collection consists of miscellaneous records of the center, mostly dating from the 1970s. The correspondence files include letters to and from UWM administrators concerning the center, including the Dean of the College of Letters & Science Joseph G. Baier and Director Clifford H. Mortimer. The correspondence files document concerns over funding; the purchase of a research facility for the center; staffing, including the efforts to attract Mortimer to head the center; and research projects. Also contains some files on the Council for Marine Studies, which directed marine research at the UW campuses; the acquisition and conversion of the Research Vessel (R/V) Neeskay, including photographs of its launching; proposals and requests for additional support for the Sea Grant Program from the National Science Foundation; and the proceedings of the 1973 Conference on Port Planning and Development as Related to Problems of U.S. Ports and the U.S. Coastal Environment. About half of the collection consists of publications issued by the Center, most dating from the 1970s.
On 1 April 1963, Dean Joseph G. Baier appointed an ad hoc committee to begin planning for the establishment of a Center for Great Lakes Studies, which was to be a interdisciplinary unit consolidating research in the physical, chemical, and biological aspects of the Great Lakes. The center's first acting coordinator was appointed on 15 October 1964. The center was officially established in February 1966. Between 1964-1973, the center was administered by the College of Letters & Science; beginning in the Fall of 1973, it was administered by the Graduate School. The Great Lakes Research Facility was purchased in 1973, and is administered by UWM for the UW System.
The files are organized alphabetically by subject, then chronologically.
Publications are organized by report number in boxes 3-5. If there is no report number, then the publication is organized by the last name of the author.
Alternate Format
Selections from this collection are included in the UWM MINDS@UW collection for the Publications of the Great Lakes Center for Research.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
UW-Milwaukee College of Letters & Science Records UWM Archival Collection 1
UW-Milwaukee Office of the Provost and Vice Chancellor for Academic Affairs Records UWM Archival Collection 12
Administrative/Restriction Information
There are no access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
An unknown individual transferred the collection to the Archives prior to 1989. The provenance of the records is unclear. Many of the records in the collection were created or compiled by the dean or an associate dean of the College of Letters & Science. It is not known if these records were later brought together by the deans or the director of the center, or if they were separated from other files by University or Archives staff. The records, whatever their provenance, were placed together under the Center for Great Lakes Studies by the Archives staff sometime before 1989. When processing began in 1993, it was decided to leave the existing organization intact rather than to possibly confuse the provenance even more.
Contents List
- Advisory Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Affiliated Faculty Meetings, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- All University Marine Task Force, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Brochures, 1977-1989 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Collected Reprints, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Conference on Great Lakes Research, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Conference on Port Planning and Development, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
- Correspondence, 1963-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9-16)
- Council for Marine Studies, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Great Lakes Research Facility, 1975-1976, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- History of the Center for Great Lakes Studies, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Oceanography Committee, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Opportunities for Research, 1976? (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Pamphlets, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Photographs, 1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Presentation to the Port Industry Conference, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Program, American Society of Limnology and Oceanography, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Progress Reports, 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Publications
  - Brooks, Arthur S.
    - Investigations of the Effects of Chlorinating Power Plant Cooling Water on the Biota of Lake Michigan, 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - Investigations of the Effects of Chlorinating Power Plant Cooling Water on the Biota of Lake Michigan, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
  - Mayer, Harold M., Wisconsin's Great Lakes Ports: Background and Future Alternatives, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Mortimer, C. H.
    - Case for a Great Lakes Studies Facility at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Center for Great Lakes Studies at UWM: Present Status and Progress During the Quinquennium 1967-1972, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Development of an Automatic Vessel-Operated Temperature Depth Profiling System, 1971 (Box 5)
    - General Account of the Aims, Activities and Organization of the Center for Great Lakes Studies at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Great Lakes: General Characteristics; Multiple Uses; University Involvement, 1968 (Box 5)
    - Plan for a Fast Work Boat, 1968 (Box 5)
    - Whither Great Lakes Studies in Wisconsin, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Hogman, Walter J.
    - Construction and Evaluation of Free-Falling Net for Sampling Mesopelagic Fishes, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Special Report No. 1, Mortimer, C.H., Internal Waves and Associated Currents Observed in Lake Michigan During the Summer of 1963, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 2, Schenker, Eric, Effects of Containerization on Great Lakes Ports, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 2 (1973 Edition), Schenker, Eric, Effects of Containerization on Great Lakes Ports, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 4, Fee, Everett J.,Digital Computer Programs for the Defant Method of Seiche Analysis, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 5, Schenker, Eric, Future General Cargo Traffic and Terminal Requirements at the Port of Milwaukee, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 6, Fee, Everett, Digital Computer Programs for Spectral Analysis of Time Series, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 7, Gannon, John E. Great Lakes Plankton Investigations: A Bibliography, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 8, Gannon, John E., Studies of the Effects of Dredged Materials from Selected Great Lakes Harbors on Plankton and Benthos, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 9, Hogman, Walter J., Documentation of a Computer Program for Multispecies Fish Populations, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 10, Schenker, Eric, Overseas Shipping at Great Lakes Ports: Projections for the Future, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 11, Beeton, A.M., Statement on Pollution and Eutrophication of the Great Lakes, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 12 Part 1, Mortimer, C.H., Large-Scale Oscillatory Motions and Seasonal Temperature Changes in Lake Michigan and Lake Ontario Part I. Text, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 12 Part 2, Mortimer, C.H., Large-Scale Oscillatory Motions and Seasonal Temperature Changes in Lake Michigan and Lake Ontario Part II. Illustrations, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 13, Howmiller, R., P., Report on a Cruise of the R/V Neeskay in Central Lake Michigan and Green Bay, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Special Report No. 14, Fee, Everett J., Digital Computer Programs for Estimating Primary Production, Integrated Over Depth and Time, in Water Bodies, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Special Report No. 15, Schenker, Eric, Extending the St. Lawrence Seaway Navigation Season: A Cost-Benefit Approach, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Special Report No. 18, Beeton, A.M.Investigation of the Influence of Thermal Discharge from a Large Electric Power Station on the Biology and Near-Shore Circulation of Lake Michigan Part A- Biology, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Special Report No. 19, Rao, Desiraju B., Two-Dimensional Normal Modes in Arbitrary Enclosed Basins on a Rotating Earth: Application to Lakes Ontario and Superior, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Special Report No. 22, Sato, G. K., Investigation of the Influence of Thermal Discharge from a Large Electric Power Station on the Temperature and Near-Shore Circulation on Lake Michigan, Final Report, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Special Report No. 23, Balfe, Margaret, Analysis of International Great Lakes Shipping and Hinterland, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Special Report No. 31, Brooks, Arthur S., Effects of Intermittent Chlorination on the Biota of Lake Michigan, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Special Report No. 32, Mortimer, C.H., Internal Waves Observed in Lake Ontario During the International Field Year for the Great Lakes (IFYGL) 1972: I. Descriptive Survey and Preliminary Interpretation of Near-Inertial Oscillations in Terms of Linear Channel-Wave Models, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Special Report No. 33, Marmorino, G. O., Internal Waves Observed in Lake Ontario During the International Field Year for the Great Lakes (IFYGL) 1972: II. Spectral Analysis and Modal Decomposition, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Special Report No. 42, Mortimer, C.H., Long Internal Waves in Lakes: Review of a Century of Research, 1993 (Box 4)
- R. V. Neeskay, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Request for Support of Facilities, 1975? (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Sea Grant Program, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Sea Grant Program
  - Advisory Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - First Proposal to the National Science Foundation, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Proposal to the National Science Foundation for Continuing Support, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Proposal to the National Science Foundation for Continuing Support, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Scuttlebutt, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Steering Committee, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)